Okay we're almost through the שלשת ימי הגבלה. Sheloshay Yemei Hagbalah.
We start off with we are in דף פ"ח Daf Peh Chet
88, we start on the משנה Mishnah on פ"ז עמוד ב'. Peh
Zayin Amud Bet. Let's take a look.
Okay we are talking about the types of measures used in the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So we did with the dry measures, now
we get to the liquid measures.
שבע מדות של לח היו במקדש, Sheva middot shel lach hayu bamikdash,
there were seven liquid
measures, הין hin והן וחצי ההין vehen vechatzi hahin and a half
הין. hin. A הין hin is 12 לוג log by the way,
a לוג log and therefore רביעית, revi'it, רביעית revi'it means a quarter
in a לוג. log. A רביעית revi'it is the minimum size that
you use for קידוש kiddush to give you a sense which is
about 3.2 ounces. So a לוג log is about 14 ounces which
is a little shy of a... what's 16 ounces? What is it?
A soda can? Yeah in a bottle what's the...
well the liquid version of this... anyway... oh you're talking about like
how many...
like 16... like 4 ounces in a
gallon what is it like a quart or something? How many say
pints in how many ounces? 16. A pint?
No it's probably a quart, a quart is probably a quarter gallon.
What is 32?
Is it 32? Okay fine, pint is 32. Okay anyway okay so
anyway so a לוג log is so a לוג log is 14
ounces so right a לוג log is 14 ounces and therefore a
הין hin is 12 of those. A הין hin is 12 לוג.
log. Okay so that would be about we're back to about our
two-liter can right because a two-liter bottle of soda is like what
100 and how much is a two-liter bottle?
A liter is about 32. 32?
All right whatever I don't know I'm lost already. Anyway fine okay
so a לוג log but anyway a לוג log is about 14
ounces. So let's do it again. הין, hin, a הין hin which
is 12 לוג, log, וחצי הין vechatzi hin half of that which
is six לוג, log, ושלישית ההין ushlishit hahin right this is when
remember this is important because the תורה Torah speaks about the יין
yayin that comes with the various sacrifices. It's שלישית ההין לפר ורביעית
ההין לכבש יין. shlishit hahin lapar urevi'it hahin lakeves yayin.
So it's a third of a הין hin which is four לוג.
log. So you have a third of a הין, hin, ורביעית ההין
urevi'it hahin
a quarter of a הין hin which is three לוג, log,
וחצי לוג vechatzi log and then you get a half of a
לוג, log, ורביעית לוג urevi'it log and a quarter of a לוג.
log. Notice by the way you interestingly don't have a לוג. log.
Okay so that's the other sort of next measure after a הין
hin you have these gradations of a הין hin right a half,
a third, a quarter,
but you do not have but you do not have a לוג
log and then you have
a... no I skipped the words... רביעית הין revi'it hin you did,
you did, I'm sorry I skipped it in the
משנה Mishnah right right right... רביעית הין לוג וחצי לוג revi'it hin
log vechatzi log thank you. The לוג, log, the half לוג, log,
ורביעית לוג urevi'it log and the quarter לוג. log. Thank you. I
was wondering about that. רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer
berabbi
Tzadok omer, so רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Tzadok says
and here was Michael's suggestion yesterday, שנתות היו בהין, shenatot hayu vehin,
no
there was not different actual measuring cups. There was a one measuring
cup, a הין, hin, with lines with like little you know with
right which have got to be less accurate because I mean unless
it's transparent then you're not going to be able to see well
even if it's transparent it's probably less accurate. Anyway he said they
had one big הין hin with lines. עד כאן לפר עד כאן
לאיל ועד כאן לכבש. ad kan lapar ad kan la'ayil ve'ad kan
lakeves. So much for פר, par, it's חצי ההין לפר. chatzi hahin
lapar.
That's what it said on the measuring thing.
Maybe it said that or maybe it didn't say that you're right
maybe it said פר איל כבש par ayil keves because what is
it? It's חצי ההין לפר ושלישית ההין לאיל ורביעית ההין לכבש. chatzi
hahin lapar ushlishit hahin la'ayil urevi'it hahin lakeves. I think I quoted
the פסוק pasuk wrong before okay. So anyway it says פר איל
כבש, par ayil keves, at least that gets you up to רביעית
ההין. revi'it hahin. Okay it's question about for him whether this הין
hin thing itself went all the way down to לוג log and
חצי לוג chatzi log which maybe it did. All right. רבי שמעון
אומר לא היו שם הין. Rabbi Shimon omer lo hayu sham hin.
There was no הין hin in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. וכי
מה היה הין משמש? vechi mah hayah hin meshamesh?
They never needed anything that was the size of a הין. hin.
The biggest measure liquid measure they ever used was for a cow
which was a חצי ההין. chatzi hahin. So yes it's all relative
to a הין hin but you didn't need the הין hin itself.
There was nothing that you ever had that was a הין. hin.
So why would they... we'll see that. אלא ela so
what did they have in its stead? It's a little funny that
he assumes that he agrees to the principle that there were seven
measuring cups. So if you didn't have a הין hin what did
you have? אלא מדה יתירה של לוג ומחצה היתה שם. ela middah
yetirah shel log umachtzah hayetah sham. There was a one and a
half לוג log measure, שבה היה מודד למנחת כהן גדול shebah hayah
moded leminchat Kohen Gadol
because the מנחה minchah of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol it was
three לוג log for the entire מנחת חביתין, minchat chavitin, half in
the morning and half in the evening. So you had a לוג
log and a half measure to divide the oil for the כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol.
But you already had the other measures.
Well right obviously you could do it using the חצי לוג chatzi
log or the one לוג log and the half לוג log which
is what the
גמרא... Gemara...
I want to say follows the same rule as the סולת solet
which you have to take the whole thing and then
you take half out. That's a
good question. I don't know if the גמרא Gemara says that about
the oil whether you
have to
start with Oh, you would think
I was thinking that you'd
have
to
have a three לוג, log, but they don't have a three לוג.
log. They do. No, a
רביעית ההין reviit hahin is three לוג. log. A הין hin is
twelve לוג. log.
Okay, then they had...
none of you guys come baking in my kitchen.
You know what, if you don't have לוג, log, we'll come bake.
If you don't לוג...
log... no, they could do what we did. That's what a רביעית
ההין reviit hahin was. Okay, anyway. Okay, so he said you had
a one and a half לוג log measure.
Wait, a רביעית ההין reviit hahin they had... and this is completely...
No, because then you had to take the three לוג log and
divide it in half. Half the one, half for the morning, half
for the afternoon. Okay, לוג ומחצה בבוקר, לוג ומחצה
בין הערבים. log umchetza baboker, log umchetza bein ha'arbayim. A לוג log
and a half in the morning, a לוג log and a half
in the afternoon. So there you go.
All right, it's interesting, by the way, that you had the things,
the idea of you having like... not gradations, what are those called?
Lines, notches? I know, but they're called something. Notches.
Thank you. Okay, anyway...
the lines to indicate like within a measuring cup, have a word
for them, but I can't think of them. Anyway, anyway, it's interesting
that you have it for the liquid and you don't have it
for the solid.
That was never suggested by the... but in the end, remember you
only had anyway two measurements for solid anyway. All right, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: שבע מידות
של לח היו במקדש. sheva middot shel lach hayu bamikdash. There were
seven liquid measures: רביעית לוג וחצי לוג. reviit log vechatzi log. So
here's the same list except going from small to big rather than
big to small. So there was a quarter of a לוג, log,
a half a לוג, log, לוג, log, רביעית ההין, reviit hahin, which
is three לוג, log, שלישית ההין, shlishit hahin, four לוג, log, חצי
ההין, chatzi hahin, six לוג, log, והין, vehin, and a הין. hin.
דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the opposite: הין וחצי הין ושלישית הין
ורביעית הין ולוג וחצי לוג ורביעית הלוג. hin vechatzi hin veshlishit hin
vereviit hin velog vechatzi log vereviit halog. Exact same list, just the
other way. The גמרא's Gemara going to say, what is the point
of saying the same list in one direction or the other? No,
the גמרא Gemara will get to that.
But didn't he say above לא היה
שם הין?
lo hayah
sham hin? רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
Someone said... right, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we're going to get to
that. Oh, so right, right now we're going to get רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Here we have a רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, which we didn't have in our משנה. Mishna. רבי שמעון
אומר לא היה שם הין, וכי הין מה היה משמש? Rabbi Shimon
omer lo hayah sham hin, vechi hin mah hayah meshamesh? They didn't
have a הין. hin. What would they have used a הין hin
for? אלא את מה אביא תחתיו? ela et mah avi tachtav? What
will I bring in instead? אלא מידה יתירה של לוג ומחצה היתה
שם. ela middah yetirah shel log umchetza hayetah sham. It was a
לוג log and a half measure שבה היה מודד לחביתי כהן גדול.
shebah hayah moded lachavitei Kohen Gadol. They would use it to measure
for the oil for the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. לוג ומחצה בבוקר,
לוג ומחצה בין הערבים. log umchetza baboker, log umchetza bein ha'arbayim. A
לוג log and a half in the morning, a לוג log and
a half in the afternoon. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said back
to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, "That's what you need a separate measure
for?" חצי לוג היתה שם. chatzi log hayetah sham. There was a
half לוג log measure. תשלש לחצי לוג. teshaleish lechatzi log. Take three
half לוג, log, right? So you use a half cup and you
do it three times, like when your recipe calls for a cup
and a half, you take your half cup and you do it
three times. So you need a whole special measure for a מחצה...
mechetza... for a לוג ומחצה? log umchetza? אמר להם, amar lahem, he
said back to them, אף לדבריכם חצי לוג ולוג לא יעשה רביעית
היתה שם. af ledivreichem chatzi log velog lo ye'aseh reviit hayetah sham.
He says, it's not about efficiency. I mean, you know, you could
have done without bigger measures. Why do you need a half לוג
log measure? Use your רביעית reviit twice. Why do you need your
full לוג log measure? Use your half לוג log twice. So of
course you could do without it. It's still we're going to set...
make a separate measure if it's the regular thing that we need.
ואפשר לשער ברביעית. ve'efshar leshaer bereviit. You could have used your... you
know, use your רביעית reviit twice to get a half לוג. log.
Why do you need a half לוג? log? אלא זה הכלל היה
במקדש. ela zeh haklal hayah bamikdash. This was the principle: כלי שמשמש
מידה זו אינו משמש מידה אחרת. kli shemeshamesh middah zo einu meshamesh
middah acheret. A vessel used for one measure you don't use for
another. Now it doesn't mean that each measurement you could only use
for one type of a thing. I mean, there were a couple
of things that might have all been a לוג. log. But it
means that if you have like... if you have like a particular
function that needs a specific measure, you'd rather create a separate measure
for that rather than use something else, sort of like in multiples.
So if you're going to have a need for a half לוג,
log, you make a half לוג log measure rather than using a
רביעית reviit twice. If you're going to have a need for a
לוג ומחצה log umchetza measure, you make a לוג ומחצה log umchetza
measure rather than a half measure three times. They did not have
a good back answer. תוספות Tosafot says, if you want to hear,
תוספות Tosafot provides what an answer could be. If you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, לרבנן lerabbanan he says, first line top of the page,
רבנן סברי דלא דמי דמידה של לוג ומחצה לא צריכה אלא לחביתים
אבל חצי לוג צריך למילי טובא. Rabbanan savri dela dami demiddah shel
log umchetza lo tzerichah ela lachavitim aval chatzi log tzarich lemilei tuva.
So it says, yeah, if you need something... if you're going to
use, you know, a one and a half לוג log measure, you
only need like twice a day. So you use your half לוג,
log, no big deal. The other types of things you need on
a very regular basis, so you therefore in those situations you're going
to create a separate measure for it. Okay, fine. Now the גמרא
Gemara says... fine, that's it. So now the גמרא Gemara says מאי
איכא? mai ika? Now we get to the real... that's the ברייתא.
braita. Now we're going to analyze it step by step. So this
first part is of course the bizarre debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda where they don't seem to be
debating, just giving a list in one order or the other. Well,
let's take a look. מאי איכא בין רבי מאיר לרבי יהודה? Mai
ika bein Rabbi Meir l'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the difference between them? אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so says רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, בירותי
מדות
איכא בינייהו. Beirutei midot ika beinaihu. So this is what like relates
to what we just discussed yesterday, the overflowing of the measure, that's
their debate. What's that called when you have the water tension holding
stuff up? A meniscus? No.
A meniscus is the thing in your leg.
No, it isn't. No, I remember from chemistry class or something, there's
something called a meniscus.
A
meniscus is the thing in your leg.
Meniscus
is
the thing in your knee.
There's something that sounds like that. Anyway, okay. Anyway, okay. Viscosity is
the liquid.
Maybe that's what I'm thinking of. I don't know. Okay, anyway, it's
the water tension that's keeping... anyway, fine. So there's the question about
whether that overflow that's not in the vessel itself is also sanctified
by the vessel. How does that relate to just whether you're listing
it up or down? So let's take a look. By the way,
I'll remind you that what the גמרא Gemara says yesterday is that
according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, one of the dry measures included
a heaping measure, which suggests, now that's solid and this is liquid,
but that certainly suggests that for him, even the stuff that goes
over is sanctified by the vessel, well, at least by the solid.
So let's see how what the גמרא Gemara says here.
You can't have heaping with a liquid.
No, but there is surface tension will keep a... will keep there...
yeah, but you definitely, when you fill up a קידוש Kiddush cup
and you overflow it, right? Some spills, but don't you also see
that sometimes it's a little bit goes beyond the... yeah, surface tension
will keep something. I'm thinking that's a meniscus.
It's not meniscus, I'm telling you. You think you tore your meniscus?
I tore your meniscus in my leg. Alright, whatever, we'll look it
up later. My finger's feeling funny. Okay, you can look it up.
Okay, anyway, okay, google what was it.
Alright, so now we say like this. Okay, מאי איכא בין רבי
מאיר לרבי יהודה? Mai ika bein Rabbi Meir l'Rabbi Yehuda? אמר רבי
יוחנן בירותי מדות איכא בינייהו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan beirutei midot ika beinaihu.
So this... this extra amount that goes on top of the vessel.
למאן דאמר ממטה למעלה, L'man d'amar mimateh l'ma'alah,
the one who goes from small to big, that was רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, he started with the small measures and went up to
the big measures. So למאן דאמר ממטה למעלה קסבר בירותי מדות נתקדשו,
l'man d'amar mimateh l'ma'alah kasavar beirutei midot nitkadshu, that this extra stuff
is sanctified that rides on top of the surface. Why? So how
does that suggested by going from the small measures to the big?
ורביעית יהב ליה רחמנא למשה. V'revi'it yahav leih Rachmana l'Moshe.
So God gave Moses, as it were, you know, the רביעית revi'it
measure. He says here's a רביעית. revi'it. Okay.
ואמר ליה שער, V'amar leih sha'er, so use this to... to... like
to measure, דקאיילי ביה בירות. d'ka-ayilei beih beirutei. And therefore the extra
amount will go in. Basically, the way רש״י Rashi explains it is
like this. If you start with... what measure do you start with
to get the other measures? If you start with the small one,
which is always the easier one anyway, and you add multiple small
things to create a big measure, right, so you start, you're given
the standard for the small and then you add them together to
create big. So רש״י Rashi says what happens? If you have a
small thing and you're going to pour it into a larger amount,
so you can deal with a little bit of extra liquid and
then when you... because even though it's barely being held by the
surface tension, if you quickly just dump it in, you'll get it
all will go in. But he says if you try to do
the reverse, you have a large amount, let's say you've got a
רביעית revi'it and you're trying to pour... a לוג log and you're
trying to pour it into four equal vessels to make a רביעית,
revi'it, or two equal to make a חצי. chatzi. So because if
you try to pour a large amount and get it into a
smaller vessel, if you have ever... like has happened at קידוש, Kiddush,
think about קידוש, Kiddush, right? If you fill up the cup to
the top, it's the perfect example. Fill up the cup to the
top and you try to pour into these little cups to divide
out, it spills, right? So you have to be below the surface
if you want to do a good operation there. But what you
can do is you can pour it into your glass, right, you
dump it into your glass and from there you can pour it
out. So to hold the surface tension and to get it all
the liquid in, you have to pour into a larger vessel. If
you're pouring into smaller vessels, you're going to lose that extra amount.
So that's the way רש״י Rashi explains this גמרא. Gemara. So he
says if we start counting from small to big, it means we
start with a small measure, we add up small measures to get
big, we're able to capture this extra amount that's hovering over. Whereas
if you start with the big and you divide it to get
small, you can't have this extra amount because it'll just spill away.
Who says there is an extra amount to begin with though?
I guess the assumption will be that naturally there will be, if
you try to fill it up to the top to get the
full amount, naturally there will be a little bit of an extra
and their question is will that be preserved or not? Depends if
you're transferring into larger vessels or smaller vessels.
But wasn't רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir the one that says he's like
a גדוש? gadosh?
Yes, so that I don't understand about how that fits with רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir before about the גדוש gadosh unless there's some difference
between solid and liquid. I haven't had a chance to see if
anybody discusses it. Do you have something to add to this discussion
though? No.
Okay, I was thought something new. The reason that hot water works
better for washing dishes... Yes... or for cleaning things in general is
with the higher temperature it has a lower surface tension and so
it gets inside the pores more easily.
Oh, that's interesting.
Okay, yes,
I want to look at that מדרש Midrash about God giving Moses
the measurement. Like all the
measurements? Well... you know בבא בתרא Bava Batra says
a רביעית revi'it
of this and a רביעית revi'it of that.
Yeah.
So this is assuming that God he gave him just one and
משה Moshe then took that one רביעית revi'is and said, okay, make
multiples of this. Oh, I don't
know, it's—it's funny, that whole יהבי ליה רחמנא, yahvei leh Rachmana, I
agree. I mean, the whole way in which
there's sort of a הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha l'Moshe miSinai and I mean look, that's strange about the whole
thing, you know, we saw that yesterday when it spoke about the
dry measure where it sort of learned it out from פסוקים, psukim,
like where are you getting... I mean it is true the Torah
says with the הין, hin, חצי הין, chatzi hin, so it's obviously
assuming that משה Moshe knew how much the measure was, so it's
inserting into there the idea that it's almost like God said, here,
use this as your measuring cup. But you're right, it's very strange
where they're—where they're creating...
if they were standard measures, you wouldn't need to be shown at
all. Right, it's like, you know, no one needs to... Right.
But I will say while we're talking, for example, sometimes יהבי ליה
רחמנא yahvei leh Rachmana is meant a little bit non-literally. Like, for
example, another classic example when you're dealing with שיעורין shiurin is that
the גמרא Gemara has a question about what's the story with פרוץ
כעומד, parutz k'omed, meaning, let's say you have when you're dealing like
with a מחיצה, mechitzah, if you have exactly equal the amount that
is open space, like it's done with, let's say, you know, bars,
so it's not the whole thing is a wall. What happens, and
I'm not talking about רשות היחיד reshus hayachid like for שבת Shabbos
הלכות halachos or whatever. What happens if, you know, the exactly equal
the amount, the open space and the—and the walled space? So the
גמרא Gemara says, well, one person says it's good, one says it's
no good. One says הכי אמר רחמנא למשה גדור רובא. hachi amar
Rachmana l'Moshe gdor ruba. God said to משה, Moshe, make most of
it, enclose it. And the other says no, what God said to
משה Moshe is don't leave most of it open. Now, are they
really saying God said that to משה, Moshe, or are they—is that
a way of articulating what is the concept of a מחיצה? mechitzah?
The concept of a מחיצה mechitzah
to enclose it mostly or to not leave it mostly open? So
sometimes, and it's interesting that there also it's about a שיעור, shiur,
you know, about how do you measure things, how do you determine
what exactly is demanded. So I don't know how much literally I
would take this idea of God is saying to משה Moshe as
much as their understanding that this is what the Torah is demanding
in terms of how to determine שיעורין. shiurin. But you do... I
mean, it is true that in general the גמרא Gemara says that—that
שיעורין shiurin are הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe miSinai. So that maybe
is what brings God in more directly into this conversation. It is
very funny, you know, that when we say, you know, it's like
when we talk about what does the Torah demand, somehow, you know,
you automatically call this a מדרש. Midrash. You don't say, well, that's
a מדרש. Midrash. You know, we're talking about the halakhic demand, so
we say the Torah demands. As soon as you say, well, what
is God saying, all of a sudden it makes us think much
more as a narrative and as a מדרש. Midrash. But I'm not
sure it's really, you know, it's that radical of a shift here
in the גמרא. Gemara. Yeah.
And so if—if the—is the משנה Mishnah talking about did they have,
you know, a bunch of כלים, keilim, did they have a bunch
of לוגס lugs and a bunch of—or is it talking about like
the—the gold standard measure? Like they used to, for a meter, the
definition used to be whatever the meter stick long stick was kept
in wherever in France. Right. So was there such a concept, an
official לוג lug or an official something kept somewhere?
I have no idea. It doesn't seem like it. Right. It doesn't
seem like it. Right. Right. I don't see a hint to that.
Yeah.
But you know, the other thing that's a parallel to Rosh Chodesh
discussions, like, you know, כזה ראה וקדש, kaze ra'eh v'kadesh, with those
when God is actually showing, so הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu
מראה באצבע. mareh b'etzba. Right.
Here it's more, you know, יהבי ליה רחמנא... yahvei leh Rachmana... right,
I don't—I see this, it is funny that it brings God into
the conversation as opposed to the Torah demand, but
I'm saying
יהבי ליה
רחמנא...
yahvei
leh Rachmana... it doesn't say God showed him. Right, right.
It is interesting why the גמרא Gemara shifts that way. I agree.
Okay, so אמר ליה שיער דקאיילו ביה רוצם. amar leh shi'er d'ka
ayilu bei rutzim. So therefore the רוצם, rutzim, the extra amount from
the surface tension goes in when you add small measures into a
big measure, the extra gets captured. למאן דאמר ממעלה למטה, l'man d'amar
m'ma'alah l'matah, but Rabbi Meir that goes from big small, so he
presumably is saying you start with a big measure and you divide
it to get the smaller measure.
רביעית revi'is is really a little bit bigger than—than a לוג. log.
Wait. A רביעית... revi'is... well, yeah, yeah, right, right. ממעלה למטה קסבר
בירוצי מדות לא נתקדשו, m'ma'alah l'matah kasvar beirutzey middos lo niskadshu, that
they are not sanctified, ויהבי ליה רחמנא למשה, v'yahvei leh Rachmana l'Moshe,
God gave to משה Moshe the large measure, the הין, hin, ואמר
ליה שיער
בהאי, v'amar leh shi'er behai, use this, and then divide this into
halves and quarters and whatever and twelfths, דקנפיק בירוצין נפקי בירוצין, d'kanafik
beirutzin nafki beirutzin,
so the בירוצין beirutzin will spill away because when you transfer it,
that extra will spill. I question how do you know it's just
the extra will spill and not even more than that, but okay.
And yes, it's also—is a problem that this Rabbi Meir earlier spoke
about having the heaping measure, and here we're saying that he's not
saying—he's saying the extra amount does not get sanctified. But yes, that
is one way of explaining the רוצם. rutzim. Now let's see what
the next thing the גמרא Gemara says. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, Abaye
says no, דכולי עלמא בירוצי מדות, d'chuli alma beirutzey middos, everybody could
say when it comes to the extra amount of the, you know,
surface of the liquid tension, איכא דאמר נתקדשו איכא דאמר לאו נתקדשו.
ika d'amar niskadshu ika d'amar lav niskadshu. They could hold either way,
they could hold it is sanctified, isn't sanctified, I don't know how
they hold about that, but that's not their debate. והכא במלאים קמיפלגי.
v'hacha bimlei'im kamifligi. Last week's פרשה, parsha, שניהם מלאים סלת shneihem mlei'im
soles בלולה בשמן למנחה. blulah bashemen l'mincha.
So there, if you remember... way way back I even forget where
the גמרא Gemara was, it spoke about using that פסוק pasuk to
refer to liquid measures, 'cause although it speaks about סולת, solet, it
was assuming like סולת solet mixed with oil or something. Anyway, it
uses that as a model for liquid measure and it says filled.
So we're debating what does it mean to fill? So let's see
what that means. במלאים קמיפלגי. Bemile'im kamiflagi. מאן דאמר מלמעלה למטה, Man
de'amar milma'la lemata,
so the one that says you're going from top down, which is
Rabbi Meir, so therefore קסבר, kasavar, he's of the opinion מלאים שלא
יחסר ושלא יותיר. mile'im shelo yachsar veshelo yotir.
When it means filled it means exactly, no less, no more, exactly
that amount. That's how you measure. ומאן דאמר ממטה למעלה, Uman de'amar
mimata lema'la,
but the one, Rabbi Yehuda, that's going from the small measures to
the big, מלאים, mile'im, what does it mean filled? שלא יחסר Shelo
yachsar means don't have
less, אבל יותיר, aval yotir, but if you overfill it, מלאים קרינא
ביה, mile'im karina bei, that is מלאים. mile'im. Now, two questions: how
is this first of all indicated by the way they count the
vessels, you know the measures big up or down? And number two
is how is that different than the idea of ביוצי מידות? bevutzei
midot? Isn't ביוצי מידות bevutzei midot exactly the same? So תוספות Tosfos
gives the simple explanation that it's really the way this ties into
whether they're doing the vessels up or down is really that that's
just a סימן. siman. Meaning if I'm when I'm calling the vessels,
talk about the small ones and getting bigger, I'm signaling the idea
somewhat like that more is better, that I'm okay moving up. So
if I'm okay moving up, it means that when you're told to
fill a small vessel, if you overfill it then and you were
told to bring a הין hin and you bring like a הין
hin and a little bit extra, it's okay. But whereas if I
start with big and go down, I'm really indicating no no no,
you know these there are maximums here as well, not just minimums.
And therefore it's not okay to do more. That's what תוספות Tosfos
says, it's more like a סימן siman than it really is anything
else. רש"י Rashi says that a similar idea to when you put
the small to make the big, except here instead of talking about
the overflow he talked about the froth. It's a little complicated in
רש"י, Rashi, let's just work with תוספות. Tosfos. More interestingly is the
question about how is this any different than the idea of ביוצי
מידות? bevutzei midot? Isn't ביוצי מידות bevutzei midot exactly the same? So
תוספות Tosfos hints to this idea and the אחרונים Achronim elaborate and
they say no. There's two separate questions. One question is what is
the Torah asking for me when it comes to the amount that
I have to make the מנחה. minchah. Let's say, or let's say
the oil or the wine or so on. So if the Torah
says bring a, bring a you know three הין, hin, excuse me,
three לוג log of wine, can I bring 3.1? Has that somehow
invalidated because I've brought more than I needed to? That's one debate,
whether I'm allowed to bring, not that I should bring more, I
should try to, but you know a little bit extra's okay, it's
not a maximum or a strict maximum. That's one question. I might
still hold that if I overflow, the extra amount doesn't get sanctified,
okay? But so it's not sanctified, but if I bring more it's
okay, but it only becomes sanctified let's say when I take it
out of the measuring vessel, for example, and put it into another
כלי שרת. kli sharet. You understand? So if this is the measure
cup and I overflow, there's one question of if this overflow sanctifies.
There's another question is can I bring the overflow, which are not
exactly the same question. So I could say I'm allowed to bring
the overflow but it doesn't get sanctified, the way it gets sanctified
is when I pour it into another כלי שרת. kli sharet. Or
I could say the reverse: it does get sanctified, but if I
bring that
then I've brought too much, so it's sanctified but I have to
remove the extra and only bring the exact amount and then do
something else with this, you know get rid of it or use
it for some other קרבן. korban. They really are... the little extra
liquid on the top. So they really are separate questions. One question
is does the object get sanctified or not? There you could say
yes or no, that was the first question. The other question is
are you allowed to go a little bit over when you're trying
to bring the right measure. So they really are separate questions. Okay,
so that's the way אביי Abaye understands the debate. So let's keep
on going. Okay. Question. Yes. Very fast.
Yes. I'm just not able to visualize this. If you have a
liquid measure and it's filled to the top to measure correctly, anything
more is going to...
isn't that going to stay? No, surface tension. Have you ever seen
people that overflow their קידוש Kiddush cup?
You know the stuff is pouring on the...
what?
Falling, pouring down?
If you really overflow then it pours down, but if you just
overflow a little bit, just enough, there's a little bit that stays
on the top because of surface tension. And then if you quickly
spill it into a larger thing then you capture that extra. That's
just reality. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says what? Amazing.
Alright, I
having made קידוש Kiddush a lot of times they can tell you
that's true. Okay, anyway, אמר מר. amar mar.
So finishing this ברייתא, braita, Rabbi Shimon...
I've never successfully poured it without spilling.
Even into a large glass? Oh into a large... So you hold
it up here, right, and then you quickly dump it. That's what
רש"י Rashi said before, that's why the small ones, if you put
them into a bigger measure, you can capture that extra amount.
Oh because if it's wide...
if you put it into a smaller
that's wider... It has to be wider, right. Okay, anyway, alright, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, אמר מר, amar mar,
and now finishing this ברייתא, braita, Rabbi Shimon... רבי שמעון אומר לא
היה שם הין. Rabbi Shimon omer lo haya sham hin. There was
no... who needed a הין? hin? You never had anything that was
a הין. hin. You could start with the half הין. hin. So
שפיר קאמר להו רבי שמעון לרבנן. shapir ka'amar lehu Rabbi Shimon le-Rabbanan.
He made a good point for רבנן. Rabbanan. The Rabbis would say
back: הוי הין דעבד משה לשמן המשחה. havi hin de-avad Moshe le-shemen
ha-mishcha. No, they still preserved the הין hin that Moshe used for
the anointing oil. דכתיב, de-chtiv, I know, דכתיב שמן זית הין. de-chtiv
shemen zayit hin.
So God says to him to you know make this שמן, shemen,
this oil to anoint all the vessels of the משכן Mishkan and
it says
a הין hin's worth of oil. So he obviously had a... so
he measured it with a full הין. hin. מר סבר, Mar savar,
so one holds, כיון דלדורות לא הוי צריך
לפי שעה הוא דעבד וגנזו. keivan de-le-dorot lo havei tzarich lefi sha'ah
hu de-avad ve-ganzo. So Rabbi Shimon holds: Look, they didn't need it
for later generations, so Moshe made it for that time and then
they you know they buried it, they secreted it away, they buried
it, they whatever, they put it into storage. ואידך, ve-idach, and the
Rabbis hold: No, כיון דהוה הוה, keivan de-hava hava, since it was,
it was and they preserved it. And here I was thinking like
Dov said, you know maybe they used it דווקא davka because that
became the gold standard. Then they had the הין hin that Moshe
made, so based on that you could determine everything from it. That's
if you assume that they started with a large one and then
they made the small ones based on a division of them, but
the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. It just says Moshe made it
so we kept it around even though we didn't need it afterwards.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, so now he said, ומי עביד תחתיו? u-mi
avid tachtav? So then Rabbi Shimon says: So alright I don't have
the הין, hin, what do I have instead of it? So גמרא
Gemara says: לא סגי דלא מייתי? lo sagi de-lo maity? What, you
don't... it's not good enough that you don't have something instead of
it? Who needs to bring something instead? So you have six, you
don't have seven. So גמרא Gemara says: No, כדאמר רבינא, ke-de-amar Ravina,
like Ravina says in another context, גמירי שתי סמיכות בציבור, gemiri shtei
semichot be-tzibbur, that we have a tradition that you only do סמיכה
semicha with two קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibbur, the goat that you send
away on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the פר העלם דבר של
ציבור, par hellem davar shel tzibbur, and you know the ox that
is brought when the בית דין Beis Din rules incorrectly. So the
same way he says that we have a tradition of exactly two,
הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too, גמירי דשבע מדות הלח היו במקדש,
gemiri de-sheva middot ha-lach hayu ba-mikdash,
that there were seven... that there were seven
measuring liquid measures. So if he's going to do away with the
הין, hin, he has to substitute it, and he substitutes it for
the half... one and a half לוג. log. So now the גמרא
Gemara says: רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק אומר שנתות היו בהין. Rabbi Elazar
be-Rabbi Tzadok omer shnatot hayu ba-hin. So now the משנה Mishnah says:
One minute, Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok says that you had the one
הין hin and you had these lines, these measuring lines. ולית ליה
שבע מדות? ve-leit leih sheva middot? So it seems like he doesn't
hold that there were seven different measuring vessels. He only has, at
least for the הין, hin,
he only has one measuring vessel with lines in it. He doesn't
have multiple measuring vessels. So the גמרא Gemara says: Alright, לית ליה,
leit leih, fine, he didn't hold of that tradition. You're right. But
other people held of a tradition of seven. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima,
if you want I could say, מאי שבע מדות? mai sheva middot?
What is the tradition... according to him what's the tradition of seven
measuring vessels? שבע מדידות. sheva medidot. Not seven separate vessels, but seven
separate measures. So it is true that some of the measures were
all incorporated into one vessel with lines in it with measures, but
he still holds that there were seven different measures that they used
in the בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash. Okay, so those were the different
types of measurements for liquid. And now our משנה Mishnah will now
go on to teach how they were... what types of different things
they were used for. So let's look at our next
משנה. Mishnah. רביעית מה היא משמשת? revi'it mah hi mshameshet? What would
you use the רביעית revi'it for? This is again like the 3.2
ounces or so, 3.2, 3.4. It's the size we use for minimum
size for קידוש. Kiddush. So רביעית מים למצורע. revi'it mayim le-metzora. So
for the מצורע metzora it says that you slaughter the bird on
מים חיים mayim chayim in some water that's in a vessel. So
we say that the minimum amount of water, the גמרא Gemara says
in another place, has to be the... has to be a רביעית
revi'it of water. רביעית שמן לנזיר, revi'it shemen le-nazir, and a רביעית
revi'it of oil for a נזיר nazir for also when you brought
the קרבן... korban... the קרבן korban of the
נזיר, nazir, so...
when you brought, I'm sorry, when you brought the what do you
call... when you brought the bread of the נזיר, nazir, so the
bread of a נזיר nazir you mix into it a רביעית revi'it
of oil, which the גמרא Gemara says in another place.
What about the רביעית הין revi'it hin and the כבש? keves?
This is a רביעית revi'it of לוג, log, not a רביעית revi'it
of הין. hin. A standard רביעית revi'it is a רביעית revi'it of
לוג, log, okay? This is like I said only about 3.something ounces.
Okay, so so that's what you would use the oil for. חצי
לוג מה הוא משמש? chatzi log mah hu mshamesh? Twice that, half
a לוג, log, what would you use it for? חצי לוג מים
לסוטה. chatzi log mayim le-sotah. So that's the amount of water you
would use for the סוטה sotah for like scraping the מגילה megillah
into it and having her drink.
How do they know that?
Yeah, other גמרות. Gemaras. It's most... some of this is just מסורת.
mesoret. Okay? There isn't... some of it they learn from פסוקים, pesukim,
some is just מסורת. mesoret. וחצי לוג שמן לתודה. ve-chatzi log shemen
le-todah. And for a תודה, todah, for the bread of the תודה
todah you would have a half of a לוג log of שמן.
shemen. Some of this was taught in earlier גמרות, Gemaras, we're not
going to go over that now. ובלוג היה מודד לכל המנחות. u-ve-log
haya moded le-chol ha-menachot. How about the full לוג? log? That was
the standard amount for מנחות. menachot. So the same way a standard
מנחה mincha was an עשרון, isaron, right, which was a like we
said, a five-pound bag of flour, the standard amount of oil used
for a מנחה mincha was a לוג, log, which is about 14
ounces of oil. Okay, which is I don't know how many cups
is that? Who knows? Okay, how many ounces in a cup? Eight?
There's eight ounces in a cup? Okay, so it's about two cups
of oil for... every five pound bag of flour. But of course
they would also have water. Okay, so that's the standard amount of
oil that was used in a
מנחה. Mincha. אפילו מנחה של שישים עישרון נותנים לה שישים לוג. Afilu
Mincha shel shishim isaron notnin lah shishim log. Even if you had
a מנחה Mincha of sixty עישרון, isaron, you would use the לוג
log measure meaning and you would take this לוג log and you
would measure it out sixty times as opposed to taking something that
was actually like a רביעית ההין revi'it ha'hin or חצי ההין chatzi
ha'hin which actually is like you know six לוג log and use
it five times, no. They would use the לוג log measure and
use it multiple times. That's sort of like the early גמרא Gemara
that says even if you have a מנחה Mincha that's multiple עישרונות,
isronot, you use the עישרון isaron multiple times, so here you use
the לוג log multiple times and there's a parallel, right? Remember they
did not have a measure bigger than an עישרון. isaron. So if
you're going to bring a sixty עישרון isaron מנחה, Mincha, you're going
to use sixty, you're going to measure sixty times with the עישרון,
isaron, you'll measure sixty times with the
לוג. log. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer
אפילו מנחה של שישים עישרון afilu Mincha shel shishim isaron אין לה
אלא לוגה. ein lah ela logah. No, even if the מנחה Mincha
is sixty עישרון, isaron, you never use more than a לוג. log.
You might increase the flour of a מנחה, Mincha, you can dedicate
a מנחה, Mincha, a standard מנחה Mincha is an עישרון. isaron. Let's
first talk about how do you get a מנחה Mincha of sixty
עישרון? isaron? Because when you bring your private מנחה Mincha and you
make your נדר, neder, you can dedicate a מנחה Mincha that is
larger than the standard. You can say I'm going to bring a
twenty עישרון isaron מנחה. Mincha. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says when
you do that you can only choose to bring a larger מנחה
Mincha in terms of the flour, the oil remains a constant and
you will only bring one לוג log of, now again you'll say
how would you knead it? But remember you're always adding water, you're
not really kneading it, the oil is added but there's always this
assumption that you're adding water. שנאמר למנחה ולוג שמן. Shene'emar lamincha velog
shamen.
This is what you bring for the מנחה Mincha and a לוג
log of oil, so he reads it as a מנחה Mincha only
gets a לוג log of oil. Now why does it mention sixty
עישרון? isaron? Maybe it just uses it as a large number? Because
we're going to see in a later משנה Mishna that if you
make a, if you dedicate to bring something more than sixty עישרון,
isaron, you have to divide it into two separate מנחות Menachot because
it's not possible to do a good mixture
to be בולל bolel or בילה bilah if it's more than sixty,
if it's more than sixty עישרון isaron of flour. The famous phrase
כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו kol haraui levilah ein bilah
me'akevet bo means that's talking about that if you don't mix it
it's still good if you could mix it, means if it's sixty
עישרונות isronot of flour or less, okay which is again a huge
amount, sixty five pound bags of flour, that's huge, right? But anything
more than that is considered way too big and not possible to
even effectively turn into dough. So that's why it uses this as
the amount. Okay, so there's the debate of when you have a
large מנחה Mincha do you bring a multiple of לוגים logim and
use the לוג log multiple times or do you only bring one
לוג? log? And now it ends by saying שישה לפר וארבעה לאיל
ושלושה לכבש. Shisha lapar ve'arba'a la'ayil veshlosha lakeves. You would have six
לוג log for the פר par which is half of the הין,
hin, and four for the איל ayil which is the שלישית ההין,
shlishit ha'hin, and three for the ram which is the רביעית ההין.
revi'it ha'hin. שלושה ומחצה למנורה. Shlosha vamachetza lamenorah. You would have three
and a half לוג log for the מנורה. menorah. חצי לוג לכל
נר, chatzi log lechol ner, a half a לוג log for every
נר ner because the assumption is that you need a half of
a לוג log in order to burn through the longest nights of
the winter, and therefore that would be the standard amount that they
would use all the time is a half a לוג log per
lamp and there are seven lamps, so seven times a half is
three and a half לוג. log. Okay, now it is interesting that
yes that here we're measuring in לוגים logim although the whole point
is to say how they use the measures of the previous משנה
Mishna and these things like for the cow and the ram and
the lamb actually you would not use the לוג log measure you'd
use the חצי הין, chatzi hin, רבע הין reva hin and שלישית
הין. shlishit hin. But now it's just I guess making it clearer
to tell you how does that, you know what that equals in
terms of לוג. log. Okay, Gisber, I have a question. Yes.
Because in the, just mechanically on the מנורה, menorah, so in the
summer nights since you're using the same measure as the winter, right,
it would burn into the morning.
Right, no, so does that mean that everything just started a little
later because or they just extinguish it?
They would extinguish it if it was still burning in the morning,
well except for the נר מערבי. ner maaravi. Right. Yes, but they
would extinguish it if it was still burning in the next morning.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Just before you started yes the מנורה menorah had to go out
before you started?
Yes, the גמרא Gemara says I'm going to talk about that a
little because actually today we're going to talk a little bit about
how they would light the מנורה, menorah, but the basic assumption, the
רמב"ם Rambam has an interesting position which I'll talk about, but basically
there's a מצוה mitzvah of הדלקה hadlaka of the מנורה menorah at
night and of fixing it and cleaning it and fixing it in
the morning. So what the גמרא Gemara would say is that when
you came in the morning and it was time to like clean
it out and get rid of the ashes and clean it, if
something was still burning you would extinguish it so that you could
clean it,
except for the נר מערבי ner maaravi where they did the things
so that it would last till either by נס nes or by
manufactured it would last till the next night. But yes that's the
general assumption, we'll talk more about that in a little bit.
If there was extra oil could they use it for something else
or?
No, they would they would pour it out. Yes. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, יתיב רבי וקא קשיא ליה, Yativ Rabbi
veka kashya leih, it would be a lot of waste. יתיב רבי
וקא קשיא ליה, Yativ Rabbi veka kashya leih, maybe what they would
do is they would make a thicker wick and I'm serious. No
I'm serious, you know if they had an idea you always use
a certain amount of oil so maybe in the, I said the
long, right maybe in the short summer nights they would use thicker
wick so that it would burn through. It would burn out by
the morning. I don't know. יתיב רבי וקא קשיא ליה, Yosiv Rebbe
ve-ka kashya leh, so Rebbe was sitting and he was bothered. רביעית
למה נשפכה, Revit lama nishpecha, if that's all you used the רביעית
revit for, what the משנה mishna said, the מצורע metzora and the
and the what do you call it
and the נזיר, nazir, so who really why did they bother anointing
it? Who needs it as a כלי שרת? kli sharet? אי מצורע,
ei metzora, if it's to be used for the water of the
מצורע, metzora, חוצה הוא, chutza hu, so they did that outside of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the purification of the process of the
מצורע, metzora, with the water of the bird and dipping the bird
in and letting the bird go free. So you didn't need a
כלי שרת kli sharet for that. You didn't need the רביעית revit
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for that. ואי נזיר, ve-ei nazir,
and if it's for the oil that goes into making the bread
of the נזיר, nazir, לחם נזיר בשחיטת איל הוא דקדיש, Lechem nazir
bishchitas ayil hu dekadesh,
because the bread is linked to the שלמים shlamim of the נזיר,
nazir, so anytime you have a מנחה mincha linked to an animal
קרבן, korban, it gets sanctified by the slaughtering of the animal קרבן.
korban. So you don't need the כלי שרת kli sharet to sanctify
it. So who needs this measure to be a כלי שרת? kli
sharet? Now he's assuming that it was a כלי שרת, kli sharet,
that's not necessarily true. If you might remember that the גמרא Gemara
before had a whole discussion, for example, whether מידת יבש נתקדשה, midas
yavesh nitkadsha, that maybe these were measurements they had in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash but not כלי שרת, kli sharet, maybe they didn't
sanctify. But Rebbe is assuming that no, we're going to take for
granted that even though there was a debate about that by dry
measures, we're taking for granted that the liquid measures were כלי שרת.
kli sharet. Who needs it to be a כלי שרת kli sharet
if you would only use the רביעית revit for things that either
were out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or could become sanctified
through the שחיטה shechita of the
animal? So let's see his answer. אמר ליה רבי חייא, Amar leh
Rabbi Chiya, Rabbi Chiya said to him, שבה היה מודד לחביתי כהן
גדול רביעית שמן לכל חלה וחלה. she-ba haya moded le-chavittei Kohen Gadol
revit shemen le-chol challah va-challah. He says ah, because the חביתין chavittin
of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol we said that it was what?
It was a לוג log and a half for the morning and
a לוג log and a half for the afternoon. Remember we just
said that, right he had the לוג log and a half to
split it up. לוג Log and a half, how many חלות? challos?
Six. So what's six divided by a לוג log and a half?
Six quarters is one and a half, right? Got it? A לוג
log and a half divided by six is six quarters, that's one
and a half. So a six quarter, a quarter is a רביעית.
revit. So in order to parcel out the oil for each חלה,
challah, not for the whole amount as one and a half but
for each חלה, challah, you would need a רביעית revit to parcel
it out. And there you want to sanctify the actual oil itself.
So he said קרי עליה, karya aleh, so Rebbe was thrilled so
he called on him the פסוק pasuk מארץ מרחק איש עצתי, me-eretz
merchak ish atzati, from a distant land comes the man of my
I think wisdom or advice, my sage, because Rabbi Chiya came from
בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and therefore Rebbe was saying
ah, ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, you gave me the right answer. Okay,
so now that's how they figured out why they needed the רביעית
revit to be a כלי שרת. kli sharet. Now we get to
the חצי לוג. chatzi log. חצי לוג מה הוה משמש? Chatzi log
ma hava mishamesh? So what did they use the חצי לוג chatzi
log for? יתיב רבי וקא קשיא ליה, Yosiv Rebbe ve-ka kashya leh,
so once again Rebbe was sitting and he was bothered, חצי לוג
למה נמשח? chatzi log lama nimshach? Who needed the half לוג log
to be a כלי שרת? kli sharet? אי סוטה, ei Sotah, what
does our משנה mishna say you use the half לוג log for?
For the water for the סוטה. Sotah. But one minute, וכי חולין
הוו דצריכי לקידוש? ve-chi chullin havu de-tzrichi le-kiddush? Since when was that
water ever non-sanctified that it would need the measurement, the measuring vessel
to sanctify it? It says מים קדושים כתיב. mayim kedoshim kesiv. The
תורה Torah says you shall take holy water to use for it
which means, as we say, not it became holy in a כלי
שרת kli sharet but they took the water from the כיור, kiyor,
the water from the special laver that they had in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash that they used for washing the hands, and it
was sanctified in the כיור kiyor itself. So you didn't need a
כלי שרת kli sharet to sanctify that water. Again, he's assuming that
these were not just measuring vessels but they were כלי שרת. kli
sharet. אי תודה, ei Toda, if it's for the oil of the
תודה, Toda, same point, since that's coming with an animal sacrifice, you
don't need it to be sanctified by the כלי שרת. kli sharet.
לחמי תודה בשחיטת תודה הוא דקדשי. lachmei Toda bishchitas Toda hu dekadshi.
That can become sanctified through the slaughtering of the תודה. Toda. You
don't need it to be sanctified through through a כלי שרת. kli
sharet. אמר ליה רבי שמעון בר רבי, amar leh Rabbi Shimon ber
Rebbe, so now before it was Rabbi Chiya who gave him his
answer who was I think his nephew, now his son is giving
him his answer. So here's what his son said to him. His
son said to him שבה היה מחלק חצי לוג שמן לכל נר
ונר. she-ba haya mechallek chatzi log shemen le-chol ner va-ner. Ah, but
you needed it to divide out the oil for the מנורה. menorah.
We said that you would use three and a half לוג log
of a מנורה, menorah, half of a לוג log for each lamp,
so you needed the half לוג log measure to divide it out
and you needed the oil to be sanctified if you're going to
use it for the מנורה. menorah. אמר ליה, amar leh, so Rebbe
said to him נר ישראל כך היה. ner Yisrael kach haya. Light
of Israel, you're right, so it was. So he quasi giving his
son this praise but using this phrase of נר ישראל ner Yisrael
as
because obviously it had to do with the lamps. תוספות Tosafot points
out that this occurs in another גמרא Gemara which doesn't have to
do with lamps but it has to do with light. So he
has that idea of נר. ner.
That's why also sometimes they say by a young תורה Torah scholar
they'll write in his name נ"י, Nun-Yud, נרו יאיר. nero yair. Right,
so that's okay, right, so okay. אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי amar
Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi what? This is source of the name of
the ישיבה yeshiva נר ישראל?
Ner Yisrael? I was wondering that.
Is this the source of the name of the ישיבה yeshiva נר
ישראל? Ner Yisrael? I was wondering that. Okay. I have to see
if it occurs in other places. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi. So now רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
in the name of רבי, Rabbi, now that we're talking about the,
that we understand that the חצי לוג chatzi log was important to
use for the oil of the מנורה, menorah, this is an interesting
גמרא Gemara that now gets to discuss exactly how they lit the
מנורה. menorah. So let's take a look. Here's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says in the name of רבי, Rabbi, נר שכבתה, ner she-kavsa,
if the light of the מנורה menorah goes out, one of the
candles,
נדשן השמן נדשנה הפתילה, nidshan hashemen nidshana hapsila, and the oil becomes,
you know, not smoky but charred, what's what do you call דשן,
deshen, ashes, it becomes filled with ashes or the or the wick
becomes ash-like, so what do you do? כיצד עושה, keitzad oseh, what
do you do? מטיבה, metivah, you clean it out, ונותן בה שמן,
ve-nosun bah shemen, you put in new oil, ומדליקה, u-madlikah, and you
re-light it. Now when are we talking about it and what are
we talking about? So רש"י Rashi says what we're talking about is
you came in the middle of the night and it burnt out,
and there's some assumption, which is a question why we have this
assumption, that you're supposed to re-light it, actually it's like an interesting
question by חנוכה, Chanukah, כבתה זקוק לה kavsa zakuk lah or not
זקוק לה. zakuk lah. So here somehow there's an assumption that if
it burnt out you're supposed to re-light it at least that it
burns through the night. Okay, and therefore you clean it out. Now
what does it mean that it says the the wick or the
oil became ashy? So our רש"י, Rashi, the כתב יד, ksav yad,
the real רש"י Rashi says that it means literally. It means if
it because if it didn't become ash-like what would you do? Just
re-light it. You have a clean wick, you have clean oil, it
blew out, you re-light it. So fine, but the רש"י Rashi here,
the printed רש"י, Rashi, which is not the real רש"י, Rashi, but
it's one that some אחרונים achronim have like a nice discussion about
because it has an interesting concept, he says no, what it means
that from the the fact that it went out that halachically means
that now you treat the wick and the oil as if it's
ashes. Since it became extinguished, it now sort of makes it now
done, it became like ashes, it's done being used and you have
to get rid of it even if it's clean. That's the way
that רש"י Rashi reads it, but our רש"י Rashi said no, it
literally means it went out, the stuff is dirty, it's not appropriate
to re-light it with dirty wick or a dirty oil, so you
have to clean it out and refill it, and there is a
sense that even if it blows out you have to make sure
it burns through the night.
They don't actually have to come and check on it though?
No, correct. And now we're going to finish reading this and then
I'll tell you about an interesting third opinion of the רמב"ם. Rambam.
So the מנורה menorah outside it was out?
No, it was in the קודש. kodesh. You didn't see it was
not inside? Yeah, it was normally you didn't see it in the
open courtyard, there was just the מזבח. mizbeach.
You had to go into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then
you'd go in to check on it.
That's a good point.
So why is it going out and there's no wind, there's no
nobody's near
it, nothing's going near it?
Well, maybe I don't know, but חנוכה Chanukah
candles go out all the time.
Yeah, I mean you know maybe the oil isn't drawing cleanly. Yeah,
there would be no wind? I don't know. You don't think any,
first of all, there were windows, not in the משכן Mishkan but
in the מקדש, Mikdash, although again the windows supposedly
they weren't the wind going coming from outside in.
I don't know. I don't know if it was totally impervious to
drafts, you know, how but anyway so okay. Anyway so that's how.
Okay. I'll tell you in a minute how רמב"ם Rambam reads this.
I also want to say before I get to that that the
רשב"א Rashba has a totally different read of this whole גמרא. Gemara.
He doesn't like the idea that he he argues based on other
גמרות Gemaros that there's no need and they would not re-light it
if it went out. So he has a whole different way of
reading this גמרא Gemara which I didn't really get a chance to
work through, but the but this פשט pshat read of this גמרא
Gemara is it blew out, you have to re-light it in order
to get it to burn through the night and this is what
you do if you can't if the stuff is ashy and you
don't want to reuse it. Yes Dov?
The wick itself
has to be קודש kodesh in some way?
Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara says that they would use the remnants
of
the
אבנטי avnetei but was that just for the שמחת בית השואבה Simchas
Beis HaShoevah did they say they did that for the standard use
of the מנורה? menorah?
It doesn't say so with the old.
Yeah, that's what I was remembering as well but I'm trying to
remember if they say that's just for the things that they did
for שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis HaShoevah or they did it for
the regular מנורה. menorah. I don't know, but yeah presumably they would
have to be sanctified too, correct. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
says like
this. יתיב רבי זריקא וקמיבעיא ליה. yasiv Rabbi Zrika v'ka mibaya lei.
So before רבי Rabbi was sitting and trying to figure something out,
now רבי Rabbi said something and רבי זירא Rabbi Zera was trying
to figure it out. כשהוא נותן בה שמן, k'shehu nosen bah shemen,
when he's refilling this oil to re-light these lamps that blew out,
כמדת ראשונה או כמה שחסרה? kemidat rishonah o kemah she-chasra? Do you
full do you put in a full amount of oil, the full
לוג, log, right, excuse me half of a לוג, log, or do
you put in just you know if it burned halfway you just
fill up you just fill up the half that it burned? Because
again even if you're throwing
out all of the oil it doesn't have to burn through the
whole night anymore, right? If you came six hours into the night,
so fine you throw out the rest of the oil you refill
it, but it only has to burn another six hours. So maybe
you only put in the amount that was left and not the
full amount. So that's his
question. So אמר רבי ירמיה פשיטא דכמדת ראשונה, amar Rabbi Yirmiyah peshita
de-kemidat rishonah, obviously you'll put in the full
amount. דאי. de'ee. Okay, דאי כמה דחסרה, de'ee kema d'chasra, if you're
just putting in the amount that is lacking that you had to
refill, מנא ידעינן מה חסר? mana yadeinan mah chasar? How do you
know how much, I mean how do you know exactly how much
you know was left that you emptied out? You have no way
of figuring that out, so obviously you're going to put in the
standard amount. וכי תימא דמשייר ליה, ve-chi teima demishayer lei, so well
maybe you measure it, right? If you're throwing out the remnant oil,
you take it out, you measure it, and then you put in
an equal amount of oil to the amount that you're throwing out.
He says אם כן, im kein, שבע מידות, sheva middos, it's not
just seven liquid measures. נפשו להו מידות טובא, nafshulu middos tuva, you're
going to need a lot of measures because you're going to have
to find smaller measures to measure the remnant of oil. If you'll
ever have to do that, right? How else would you measure? So
obviously you cannot try to put in the amount of oil that
was left.
You just put in the big one and then just pour some
of it, you know, just only pour half of it of the
big one.
You mean you still estimate? Right. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't understand
that estimating is acceptable. Either you put the same amount that you
took out or you put the full
amount.
So what should we do with the rest of the oil that's
in this כלי kli you're not going to use?
Well that also, that you put by the מזבח, mizbeach, like that
you put, that, that, that's sort of like a תרומת הדשן, terumas
hadeshen, you put it near on the side of the מזבח mizbeach
near the red-hot coals. But that's not the issue here. So קרי
עליה, kari alei, so that was his argument. You can't try to
put the same amount you took out because you'd have to then
have smaller measures and we don't have smaller measures. So obviously you
put in the full amount. So קרי עליה, kari alei, he said
on him, והדרך vehadrach and your glory צלח tzaleach should be like
successful, רכב על דבר אמת, rechav al devar emes, you've ridden on
a true matter, וענווה צדק ve-anvah tzedek and a righteous and a
humble righteousness.
He's more liberal than the first.
I guess so, right. This is a few generations after רבי. Rebbi.
Okay. איתמר נמי itmar nami a similarly taught, אמר רבי אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan. So interestingly here was
in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
before was saying the first statement in the name of רבי Rebbi
and now רבי אבא Rabbi Abba is saying this in the name
of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. ואמרי לה ve-amrei lei in some say,
אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי חנינא אמר רבי. Amar Rabbi Abba Amar
Rabbi Chanina Amar Rebbi. Now there's a version that it was, that
this whole, this whole answer was already said by רבי. Rebbi. נר
שבמקדש, ner shebe-Mikdash, did I skip a line? נר שכבתה ner shekavsah
if the נר ner blew out, נשתנה שמן ונשתנה פתילה nitshana shemen
ve-nitshana pesilah
and the oil became ashy or the wick became ashy, כיצד עושה,
keitzad oseh, what do you do? מטיבה, metivah, you clean it, ונותן
בה שמן כמידה ראשונה, ve-nosin bah shemen kemidah rishonah, you put in
the oil like the original amount, ומדליקה u-madlikah and you light it.
So now we have the simple version here is that it blew
out in the night, you have to relight it to go through
the night. Two versions, the two different רש״י Rashi debate whether that's
you always throw out the remnant oil or only if the remnant
oil automatically it's like the remnant oil is unusable, or no, only
literally if the remainder oil became, became like ashy. You don't want
to reuse it, so you put in new. But the idea is
you reuse it for the night. The רשב״א Rashba has some different
way of learning the גמרא. Gemara. He claims you would not relight
it. Once it goes out, you don't have to worry about it.
But again, simple sense of this גמרא Gemara is yes, you have
to make sure it burns through the night, you would relight it,
you would put in new oil. Now the רמב״ם Rambam has a
very interesting position that everybody debates. The רמב״ם Rambam says what I
told you before about also addressing Dov's point about would you extinguish
it, is the almost universal assumption in the ראשונים Rishonim based on
a lot of גמרות Gemaros is, you know, you're מדליק madlik the
נר ner at night and, and you know, the תורה Torah also
says, בבוקר בבוקר בהטיבו את הנרות יקטירנה. baboker baboker betivo es haneros
yaktirena.
When it talks about burning the incense, it says every morning when
you are מטיב, metiv, you fix, you clean the נרות. neros. So
the general assumption is that that's the cleaning out of the, of
the lamp, getting rid of the oil and the ashes and whatever,
you know, except maybe for the נר מערבי, Ner Maaravi, and then
you light it at night. And then the amount of oil is
to go through the night. The רמב״ם Rambam says, and this is
interesting because of a concept maybe of נר מערבי Ner Maaravi of
the נר תמיד ner tamid that we have, that the מנורה menorah
would be constantly burning even through the day. And when the תורה
Torah says בהטיבו את הנרות יקטירנה betivo es haneros yaktirena in the
morning, what he means is you come in the morning and you
check to see how it's doing. And if it's burning well, fine,
then you just maybe add some oil. If let's say it burnt
out, then you clean that lamp out and you put in new
oil and you put in a new wick and then it burns
till the, he says that clean, and then he says in the
evening as well. He says it was really no different. The רמב״ם
Rambam says it was the exact same thing you did in the
morning and in the evening. In the evening as well, you looked
at it. If it was burning cleanly, fine, and then you maybe
just added more oil. If not, if it had burnt out or
if whatever, then you would clean the whole thing out. So there
would be what he says is הטבה hatavah and הדלקה hadlakah are
the same. That there's the lighting and there's fixing, and basically it
means that if it needs to be relit, so you clean it
out and you relit it. If it just needs to add oil,
added its oil, and you basically do the same thing morning and
evening, and it's constantly burning.
So they added more than just enough to burn through the night
then? They had, they had to do enough to burn for 24
hours.
Well no, because you always, at each one of those stages, you
add a half of a לוג. log. A half of a לוג,
log, let's say is 14 hours' worth. So whether you're adding it
at night or adding it in the morning, right, you're always getting
through the next stage. But for the רמב״ם Rambam again, nobody else
says this, but the רמב״ם Rambam says you would light the מנורה
menorah essentially twice a day and it'll constantly be burning. So the
way the רמב״ם Rambam reads this גמרא Gemara is not that it
blew out in the middle of the night. The רמב״ם Rambam reads
this גמרא Gemara as this is what happened in the morning. You
came in the morning, if the something had extinguished, you clean it
out, you put in new oil and you relight it. And if
something has extinguished, so you just refill the oil and you go
on, okay? So the way the רמב״ם Rambam reads this is it
was not some rare occurrence that it blew out in the night,
but this was the regular way of lighting the מנורה. menorah. Very
strange position that, you know, strange only because it disagrees with everybody
else. First of all, who needs a chandelier lit in the daytime?
But maybe that's more of a סימן siman that it's not for
the light. But anyway, but it's strange because all the other ראשונים
Rishonim disagree. They say there was lighting at night and cleaning in
the day.
Oh yeah, right, it wasn't an easy job.
I think it was like 18 טפחים tefachim but it was right,
it was not so much. It was like a what, it was
like three feet about, not even less. Yeah, yeah, but it was
on a base, it was on a big- the גמרא Gemara also
says that there were steps and it was on some type of
a base. So the question is like how big was the base?
So they took a torch, how did they get to light it?
Oh, they know, so the original light, if they had to relight
the נר מערבי, ner maaravi, that came from the מזבח החיצון, mizbeach
hachitzon, from the outer מזבח, mizbeach, but if the נר מערבי ner
maaravi was lit, they would light the other candles from the נר
מערבי. ner maaravi.
All right, so now, okay,
let's take a-
let's keep on going. Okay, we did-
now we're going to have a question about how they cleaned it
out. So let's and how it was constructed. Okay, אמר רב הונא
בריה דרב יהודה אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehuda
amar Rav Sheshet, נר שבמקדש, ner she-ba-mikdash, the candle- the lamps that
were in the Mikdash, the lamp here meaning that were attached to
the מנורה, menorah, the place that they actually put the oil
in, פרקים הוו, prakim havu, was of a- literally means of parts,
but here the way it's understood to mean is it was no,
no, no, not taken apart, here it means that it was flexible,
that they had flexible parts and they were not like rigidly attached
to the- well, it might mean that it was like, you know,
it was like jointed, you know, so it was somehow attached but
some type of a joint that you could bend it over, okay?
That's what the פרקים prakim means, it was
jointed. כסבר כי כתיב ככר ומקשה Kasavar ki ketiv kikar u-miksha that
it's all of
a talent of gold and
it's one unit, המנורה ונרותיה כתיב, ha-menorah u-neroseha ketiv, it applies even
to
the lamps. וכיון דבעי הטבה, Ve-kivan de-ba'i hatava, and since you have
to clean
it out, אי לאו דפרקים הוו, i lav de-prakim havu, if
it were
not- if they were
not
jointed, לא הוה מטיב
ליה, lo havah meitiv leh,
you would not be able to do a good job in cleaning
it out.
But at some point if you bend it again and again it's
going to snap off, no?
Depends how well it's constructed I guess.
I mean, if it's made to bend.
Right, so if it's a jointed type of a thing. You ever
buy for your kids those like wooden snakes that are jointed and
the whole thing?
That's what the- that's the idea. Recycle, you know? It doesn't break.
Okay, let's do a little bit further. Okay, מיתיבי Meseivi asked on
this, כיצד עושה, keitzad oseh, how would you clean it out? מסלקן,
mesalkan, this is a ברייתא, Baraisa, מסלקן, mesalkan, you would remove the
lamps, ומניחן באהל, u-manichan be-ohel, you would put them in an אהל
ohel which has some type of a- of a soap, of a
cleansing agent, ומקנחן בספוג, u-mekanchan be-sfog, and you'd clean them out with
a sponge, ונותן בהם שמן, ve-nosan bahem shemen, and then presumably after
you put them back on the מנורה, menorah, then you would refill
it with oil, ומדליקן, u-madlikan, and light them. So, so you see
they're removable, much easier. No, הוא דאמר כי האי תנא, hu de-amar
ki hai tanna, okay, that's one opinion, he says like the other
תנא. tanna. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, חכמים אומרים,
Chachamim omrim, the sages say, לא היו מזיזין אותן ממקומן, lo hayu
mezizin osan mi-mekoman, you would not remove them from their place. So
first the גמרא Gemara interrupts, one minute, מכלל דאי בעי לזוזי מצו
מזוזי, michlal de-i ba'i le-zuzi matzu mi-zuzi, you wouldn't remove means that
if you wanted to remove you could, it sounds like they also
hold that it was removable. So גמרא Gemara says no, no, that's
not what it means. אלא אימא, Ella eima, what they mean to
say is, לא היתה זזה ממקומה, lo haysa zaza mi-mekomah, it could-
they were not able to be moved, the lamps, they were fixed
in the מנורה, menorah, and therefore that's- he's of that opinion, that
they were part of the מנורה menorah and therefore they had to
be jointed. ומאן חכמים, U-man Chachamim, who are the חכמים? Chachamim? רבי
אליעזר הוא, Rabbi Eliezer hu, it's Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא, Detanya, רבי אליעזר
ברבי צדוק אומר, Rabbi Eliezer bar Rabbi Tzadok omer, כמין תס של
זהב היה על גבה, ke-min tas shel zahav hayah al gabah,
the מנורה menorah had like- each lamp had like a golden a-
lid- a roof on top of it, right? Because you wanted to
keep out- you know, the gook from the outside, you wanted to
protect the oil, so you had this thing that covered over- covered
over the lamp, right?
Meaning there was a little place that the wick came out, but
it was not an exposed like- when we light our מנורה menorah
things, you know, you have a big exposed place for the oil,
but they wanted to protect the oil, so it basically had a
cover on top of it with a little hole from where the
wick came out. So they had this So they had this golden
lid, as it
talks about כשמטיבה keshemayteva
when he would clean it, דוחקו כלפי פיה, dochko klapei piha, they
would push the lid towards the lip, presumably where the wick came
out with, again it’s a little unclear what it means but presumably
it means you’d lift up the lid, it would be hinged so
you could clean it. כשנותן בשמן keshunoten bashemen
and when you would put the oil in and after the oil
had been put in, דוחקו כלפי ראשה dochko klapei rosha which means
again the way רש"י Rashi says it means you would close the
lid to protect the oil. Anyway what we see from here though
is that he speaks about not moving the lamp when you’re cleaning
it but sort of keeping it all in its place and therefore
that was the assumption.
Okay, maybe just one more line. ובפלוגתא uviflugta this is already debated
elsewhere דהני תנאי dehani tannai it’s like of the following תנאי. Tannai.
דתניא detanya we learned in a ברייתא Braita מנורה ונרותיה באות מן
הככר menorah uneroteha baot min hakikar the menorah and its lamps were
all from the talent, which also presumably means the lamps were attached,
ואין מלקחיה ומחתותיה מן הככר ve’ein melkaheha umachtoteha min hakikar but the
tongs and the shovels meaning the cleaning vessels or whatever those were
not from the talent of gold. רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah אומר omer
מנורה היתה באה מן הככר menorah hayta ba'ah min hakikar no only
the menorah itself was from the talent ולא נרותיה ומלקחיה ומחתותיה באות
מן הככר velo neroteha umelkaheha umachtoteha baot min hakikar
not the lamps or the tongs or the cleaning vessels. So therefore
according to him if the lamps were not part of the ככר
kikar they actually therefore did not have to be attached either and
were detachable which made it easier. And just quote the פסוק pasuk
במאי קמיפלגי bemai kamiflagi what are they debating בהאי קרא behai kra
the following פסוק. pasuk. דתניא detanya ככר זהב טהור יעשה אותה kikar
zahav tahor ya’aseh otah she shall make it a pure gold למנורה
שבאה מן הככר lemenorah sheba’ah min hakikar the menorah comes from the
talent. מניין לרבות נרותיה minayin lerabot neroteha how do you know even
the lamps? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar את כל הכלים האלה et kol
hakelim ha’eleh and all these vessels so they’re part of the talent
and therefore presumably they’re also attached. יכול שאני מרבה אף מלקחיה ומחתותיה
yachol she’ani marbeh af melkaheha umachtoteha
maybe even these other vessels, these other cleaning vessels and tweezers תלמוד
לומר talmud lomar אותה otah it. So only something that’s part of
the actual structure not things that are like these external vessels. דברי
רבי נחמיה divrei Rebbi Nechemiah
that’s what רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah says. Okay so and we’ll just
add one line הא רבי נחמיה אהא רבי נחמיה ha Rebbi Nechemiah
aha Rebbi Nechemiah this רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah debates the other רבי
נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah because the earlier רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah said that
they actually were what do you call it that they actually were
that they were detachable and here he’s saying that they were attached.
תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי נחמיה trei tannai aliba deRebbi Nechemiah two תנאים
Tannaim according
to רבי נחמיה. Rebbi Nechemiah. Alright we’ll pick up with this tomorrow
but basically the question is did they all come from the same
talent of gold and if so they were attached so you have
to be able to clean the lamps and the question is did
you clean them because they were sort of hinged or were you
able to clean them because they were actually removable.